foreign an astounding an astounding
woman
an astounding mother
Nanda Mata
and she was apparently an anagami so the
she was apparently an anagami so the
first five lower Fetters have been
completely destroyed and
and
so these are about her astounding
qualities and she's she's actually telling uh the
and she's she's actually telling uh the
great random sari puta about these
qualities and he's saying wow that's
amazing wow that's amazing it's amazing
and there's a few that stand out really um
well the first one is that as she's
doing some recitation or or reciting
some suitors badly
there is a
a Heavenly being or a God that comes to
speak to her and praise her for that
so the fact
is that she
that gods
according to this are coming to speak to
her you know she's not sort of going to them
you know she's not sort of going to them
as a human being so which kind of shows
the loftiness of her mind I was you know
it's so
Beyond this world where even she's
conversing with gods and um
and um
so Venable study Buddha says that's
amazing that's wonderful
and she says sir this is not my only
incredible and amazing quality there is
another I had an only son called Nanda who was
I had an only son called Nanda who was
dear and pleasing to me the rulers the
the great authorities forcibly abducted
him on some pretext and had him executed
but I can't recall getting upset when he
was under arrest being arrested
imprisoned or being put in prison killed
or being killed
and when will saliput says it's
incredible it's amazing that you purify an Arisen
it's amazing that you purify an Arisen
thought I don't quite understand it but
purifying thought in the rising yeah as
soon as the thought manifested yes
there's no time for it to to accrue the
unwholesomeness the views the leanings
the cravings
he's just seen for what it is as it is
most people don't most people catch
their thoughts down the stream when it's
already polluted with this so that and
then they have to undo it back
but if the mind is developed as soon as
the thought arises is seen correctly
with right wisdom yes this is
unwholesome this should not be delighted
well I think that that's not even that's
gone now she doesn't even need to say
that anymore that's why it's so amazing
it sounds like the pure you're purify
even as it arises right yes as there
Rises it's being purified so there is no
oh and I shouldn't think this
unwholesome thoughts yeah
yeah you know what you know disgusting
is disgusting you don't have to keep
telling yourself
yeah exactly so there is no more lapsing
of the context in regard to the
immediate arising of thoughts
that's where the context penetrated
through yeah
thoughts of what my son any reason
anything anything
thought of this thought of that thoughts
that would give rise to sensuality or
real will or sadness or grief or
hindrance doesn't matter in its nature it's
doesn't matter in its nature it's
already purified before it could even
give rise to such things
seen as it's seen as a thought
it understood its nature yeah yeah
she's she can see her mind seeing the
signs of the Mind way about that point
yeah yeah it's a purifying the rising
you see the signs of your mind and then
you can start purifying the thoughts
correctly but she is already purifying the arising
but she is already purifying the arising
of the thought that's already affected
by her understanding so she doesn't even
need to purify her thoughts she's
cleaning things at the top of the spring
it's she's keeping it clean she's not
even cleaning it she's keeping it clean
so someone said well she
the son her son she obviously didn't
care she was so lucky oh yeah you can be
she was so lucky oh yeah you can be
cynical about everything but she said
herself the son she loved the son she
she raised it was very pleasing to her
so if you have a reason to think that
she was lying sure but uh
sorry Buddha didn't think that so yeah I
mean you can also think oh she sounds
very conceited
oh yes very well sorry but that's not
the only amazing quality that I have let
me tell you more about myself
I mean to an uninstructed worldling that
can sound as the after conceit in
arrogance but it's just factually true these are
but it's just factually true these are
things factually amazing
because Dharma is amazing and that's
exactly what she says
she practiced it she developed it's like
oh wow even she's surprised how amazing
these things are once you practice it
it just sounds
like oh but that's impossible you know
the only way that somebody could not
care or not be moved by such an event is
if they just become like a kind of a
robot or yeah they just don't have any
emotion or feeling or any they don't see
the significance of things anymore
which is kind of why you can't well
they're dismiss it they dismiss the
possibility because it's just
incomprehensible how that's possible
thus it's not possible because my own
limited thinking is still my reference
for what's right and wrong that's most
people basically yeah
that she was obviously she clearly knew
the significance of things my dear and
pleasing son and yes and well again she
would not have listed list that as an
amazing thing that her mind didn't move
amidst this quite a horrible experience
of having a son falsely imprisoned and
killed if she did not understand the and
kind of experience that significance the
full weight the full extent of having
your own son abducted tortured killed
all at a false pretech and you couldn't
do anything about it and yet her mind
didn't move that's the amazing aspect
he's like oh I didn't care about that
son I never saw him he was a drunkard he
was killed I didn't care well that's not
much of an accomplishment isn't it you
wouldn't list that it's a great thing
means she actually felt the full extent
of that experience yet remained unmoved
and the dhamma is wonderful because of
that and saying that other men
who also understood the perilous
sensuality the full degree of it went
back home
after being with the Buddha and said I
you know this the sexual intercourse is
Unthinkable for me anymore so told his
wives he won't he'll be celibate for the
rest of his life basically he was an
anagami if you want to stay here I'll support
if you want to stay here I'll support
you if you want to go and remarry I'll
support you I'll I'll set you up and
then he's his first wife says okay take
me to such and such man
he says now you could think oh he didn't
feel anything he was a robot but then he
would not have described the whole thing
and the significance of it because he
said no he took his first his dearest
wife the one that was longest with him
by her hand took him to that man drawing
their hands put the water over in that
ceremony of giving the blessing and he
was surprised that his own mind didn't
move at any part of that process and
then explained isn't this Dumber
wonderful once you practice it and
understand the danger of sensuality your
mind doesn't move amidst things that I'm
surprised I didn't move
so he felt the full weight of it yet he
wasn't enough to move the mind that's
freed himself from it
and that's what I say like you find a
way out of suffering amidst the
suffering and there is no greater
verification in that
and that's the one yeah for mother for a
mother son yeah in his case he was that
there's always going to be something
so the question is not about destroying
the significance of things there is no
sign telling us exactly there is no
sound there is no matter there is no
wife there is no dearness there is no
there is
yet you're not moved by it because you
train your mind in regard to that
but for most people the idea of training
is the idea of denial
oh there is no there's nothing real in
calapas are constantly flicking and
changing and atoms are flying nothing's
real nothing is real in reality it's
just these empty designations
conventions yeah good luck with that then
yeah good luck with that then
because when the confinement does come
and those secondary management
explanations don't apply anymore you're
left with which you started suffering
and not knowing the escape from it
and the difference then but we've
basically seeing it here
or Baghdad
yeah the difference would be recognizing
that it doesn't come from the from the
significance from the things from the
experiences comes from your own
resistance towards it
people would regard that as being a bad
parent even if you were actually you
know making some efforts to but not have
not being emotionally involved oh yeah
yeah of course of course yeah that would
be concerned oh it's all good but you
need to like the only way for you to
show your love is to cry and to be
emotionally disturbed but if you stop
and look at it closely the only reason
people give in to tears and emotional
disturbances because they don't want to
Bear it yeah they can't bear it so it's
a magical release of the pressure just
break down cry and then you'll feel
better after the physical fatigue sets
in so you are actually loving that
person less because you cannot endure
the extent of their significance but you
break down like a little child and cry
as a defense mechanism not as a great
love
so to take in the full significance
you know of uh yeah because that's like
you cry you don't want to face it you
act you kick you scream when your mind
moves and your mind moves when the Mind comes
and your mind moves when the Mind comes
bear the significance of it
but pressure the weight the love
whatever it is
so
it's correct to say that the only person
they can truly see the the extent of
loving your son would be at least an
anagram needs to be at least another
government or have at least the Right View
or have at least the Right View
and they'll be able to fully take the
weight of someone's
significance presence love death without
moving without fearing it they can see
how important that person was to them
otherwise they're just selfish that's
why they're crying
contrary to popular belief it's
basically difficult to remain unmoved
yes and then on top of it
you now have the view that says no no
you should be moved
on account of Love or Whatever emotion
you have that's virtuous but yeah but
then you realize well the only reason I
say I should be movies because I can't
help but move yeah if I'm honest
at least if I were to have an option to
not move okay then I can maybe decide to
move or not but I don't I just move
because you're just crushing me I just
can't bear it that's how much I love you
I that's how much I care about
avoiding discomfort in my own mind and
people do understand that like when they
say you know people are greatly in love
it's like it's a very selfish thing like
you basically almost objectify this
person that represents that love for you
because that's how self-centered you are
and yeah you'll be distraught you won't
eat for a month you'll be crying if
things but all because you're so selfish
because you can't bear it you can't bear
it on the mental level so you're doing
all these magical acts and breakdowns to
cope with it
you just don't want to face pain just
don't want to face it
yeah that's what it is and you're not
able to
yeah allow this pain to endure you have
to like yeah we have Hollywood and all
these are glamorizing yeah they're
acting out to it but actually yeah if
you just uh yeah in a way like friend
friendly with this pain then yeah you're
able to see that it's possible to not
have this Obsession to try and escape
this pain yeah and then you you could
then clearly with a with an unpolluted
kind of uh context see the significance
of that person whether it was just
essential infatuation Obsession whether
it was genuinely uh close friend or
something doesn't matter because you
would not be magically sort of inventing
things to cover up the weight
because the mind's not moved so the mind
can remain facing it seeing it
yeah that doesn't stop you from I don't
know looking after them or helping
exactly not at all not at all quite the
opposite you will do it even better if
you're not acting selfish you're not
acting out of that compulsion and
pressure and fear but also like let's
say that they do something
a bit dodgy and you're intoxicated by
your feelings towards them you're not
going to be able to help them you're not
going to be able to say to them you need
to watch out like that is what you just
did is wrong and that is the most loving
thing you can do to that yeah to to be
very firm with it what is genuinely good
for them yeah you could see that and and
maintain the perspective yeah
but for that you need to work on
yourself you don't work that by
loving others and dealing with others no
you're worried that by training your
mind how not to move amidst things they
want to move it so sense restraint
guarding of the doors and unhaul some
things on a day-to-day level these
little things
it's little thoughts little choices that
you feel like oh well I know this is
Central but I'll I'll do it no when you
recognize it when you're self-conscious
of it
you don't do it that's the practice
but if you don't think the practice is
there if you think practice is kind of
oh well you know I do my best my
precepts are more or less okay I avoid
things sometimes I sleep a bit but yeah
I spend three hours sitting cross-legged
and feeling the breath in my abdomen and
everything else
that's not the practice
I mean the Buddha never taught
meditation to lay people
you never told meditation in
contemporary sense of that word and to
anyone but
there was no anyway that he was
instructing lay people householders how
to practice
samadhi or samata yet this lady was an
anagami with John as it will
want to count to what well if you read
further suit that you'll see on account
of what on account of purifying her
thoughts since he was she was a young
girl to just do that don't do anything else
to just do that don't do anything else
just every unwholesome thoughts that
arises you purified no exception
no no rest day no cheat day during the
week that but that's all you need to do
that but that's all you need to do
don't need to go on top of a mountain
don't need to ordain
don't need to sit cross legs six hours
don't need to go to perm and do a
retreat just purify every thought that's
just purify every thought that's
unwholesome and it's arising
every single time
and then you can Yourself by taking
these amazing qualities and the gods
will come and talk to you
how would you you know especially in the
beginning like
you know it's very tricky with the
criteria that you use for false and
non-holesome um um
is either
It's Tricky if nobody if somebody hasn't
invest any thought in it whatsoever but
if you started it like I know myself
when I I didn't even I don't think I was
even I even read the sutas at that point
yet but I was I kind of
no I think I want to learn how to calm
my mind or meditation or something I had
some broad interest
and the first and the most obvious thing
like even before I educated myself was
well I can't at the same time then continue
I can't at the same time then continue
sort of drinking parting going out and
doing the same things I'm doing that's
just ridiculous I have to stop this and
then seek to educate myself further how
to thank the mind but
if you're honest it can kind of it's
clear deep down everybody would know but
say you are unclear well yeah read the
sutras and the Buddha is hammering it in
all the time Watson wholesome and then
you try and understand it for yourself
and then you'll see it
whatever you're about to do ask yourself
why you're doing it what's the reason
for it not for the sake of a great
answer or resolution just for the sake
of clarity and if it's like no this is
factually on wholesome fine I don't need
to do anything else I don't need to Now
counter these thoughts and then do this
practice no I just need to not act out
of it and endure that for as long as
it's present
and then I haven't acted out of it and
either once twice three times and it
starts by not acting out you practice it
successfully acting out will not even be an option
acting out will not even be an option
because your thoughts would be clear in
their arising
so let alone action coming out of it
that's that's just not not going to be
possible not acting out is kind of
uneventful you know so it seems like
nothing's got not what are you doing
nothing yeah you know I need something
more palpable to do as my practice for
intention it just dies yeah so you
didn't act out there
there's no fireworks yeah yeah exactly
but it's not so easy to see or
understand what
passion version delusion is but at least
what I found for myself that was just an
excuse It's like you said it's obvious
what it is but saying to myself well I'm
not so clear about this makes me able to
act out of it you emphasize basically so
you might not understand the full extent
of it and you emphasize that aspect so
that you keep acting out exactly but you
realize but wait I do understand a great
extent to it so well and to that extent
I shouldn't act then and then the rest
of it will be understood yeah so just a
little bit of honesty is needed for
everybody individually and and it's very
clear and that's exactly why some monks
and nuns in the suitors that's all they
needed in terms of the instruction
whatever you know it's on wholesome
don't do it don't cultivate it whenever
it's not it's wholesome cultivated
and it was enough as a principle yeah it
remains standing
just going with the suitors
this is number three
she says this is not my only incredible
and amazing quality there is another
my husband passed away
and he was born in one of the Realms of
the spirits
he revealed to me his previous life form
but I can't recall getting upset on that
account so she's seeing sort of spirits
so she's seeing sort of spirits
manifesting yeah something which would
otherwise be frightening to people yeah
ghost or something
but number four he says I used to be
your husband
yeah okay
number four stands out a bit to me that
she says this is another one of my
incredible amazing qualities
ever since we were both young and I was
given in marriage to my husband
I can't recall betraying him even in
thought still less indeed so even when
young she was already
doing this purifying practice well yeah
exactly yeah it's not it's not something
overnight so who who would be able
to not even have a thought about another
like in her case another man Even even a
fleeting thought
ever that's how steady unmovable and thorough
that's how steady unmovable and thorough
and transparent and clear her mind was
even when she was a young girl given
into marriage
there's something you know but again so
okay so I'm not on that level but what's
stopping you to start now
what's stopping you now to purify your
thoughts as they arise it's not because
it's like oh well she was just an
amazing person well for her yeah yeah
exactly but
but
one criticism one one
I think I heard long ago was
well you see she was she had all these
amazing qualities
and she had a son she had a husband
she wasn't celibate
she was fully engaged in sensuality oh
yeah full-on and she's still attained
the highest one of the highest goals so
so not being celibate
means she was not celibate when she had
a son
yeah that's it yeah because in other
suit is the Buddha mocks and criticizes
brahmins they're the worst than dogs
because dogs would mate only when in
season in order to reproduce
which is a higher yeah yeah so that also
if somebody wonders how far I can go
with my precepts well that's how far you
should go
technically you're not celibate
because you will reproduce to have a
Offspring that's the only excuse for not
being celibate
so that's the truly virtuous person in
terms of so yes and nothing after that
nothing before I mean nothing everything
you can now do anything that's of sexual
nature yeah of course it's all okay now
yeah yeah that's the facts it's my wife
it's my husband exactly so I can just
indulge because it's consensual or
something so and but what stands is that
even when I was young I did not portray
my husband so she didn't she had a
mentally she was disgusted by that act
even just fantasizing about it
even about another man
she was already mentally disgusted or
yeah withdrawn so it would be quite a
stress to think that physically she
wasn't yeah physically she was all about
it yeah because you will not be able to
like like even purify your thoughts on
that level if your actions are not
beautiful so you can only imagine you
know yes if somebody wants to use that
so there's an argument that they can be
not celibate and uh practice for a
anagami sure but then that not celibate
needs to be understood on the level have
sexual intercourse only for
that reproducing that's without any
passion basically doesn't matter if
passion overwhelms you whatever maybe
you need more work but engage in an Act
only to have a child
nothing else to extend the Family that's
it for the purpose of extending a family
of whatever
yeah exactly even that actually the
reason why you would have a child but
let's not get into that like back then
the entire kind of um continuation of of
parents and the the family and
everything would would depend on having
children and today that's not the case so why do
and today that's not the case so why do
you want to have children as well
so sure you don't have to be celibate
uh
on the occasion you want to you need to
have a child if those criterias are not
met well
you cannot use this suit as an argument
and that's also see
that's why she's an anagramulator yeah
she's not like oh she was so pure
because she was a nagami no it's because
she practiced this Purity she became
anagani because she was withdrawn from
sensuality she became origami I mean the
Buddha said that the mind can enter a
genre a Mark that tajana who hasn't been
withdrawn who hasn't understood the
danger gratification the escape in terms
of sensuality that's not possible
it's not possible unless you fully
abandon sensuality beforehand it's not
possible to enter China
to to experience Jannah
and another suit as he says that the
first genre is necessary for fruits of
anagami in other words anagam is free
from sensuality before he is an anagami
that's why he's an anagami because he's
free from sensuality not other way
around so this is a fifth amazing quality
so this is a fifth amazing quality
ever since I declared myself a lay
follower I can't recall deliberately breaking any
I can't recall deliberately breaking any
precept
yeah so when she
declared oh by the way yeah I am but she
when she understood them she got The
Right View for the rest of my life yeah
that's usually when people declare being
a life follower means they understood
the Dharma as as householder
and hers
and then John is six yeah there's six
amazing qualities that you can get all
genres that will yeah
and uh and then the seventh
was a
of the five lower Fetters taught by the
Buddha I don't see any that I haven't
given up
hmm see that's another thing given up
it's something you maintain you hold on
to and you see that you know that and
that's those little things that I keep
saying throughout the day little
thoughts little actions that is that is
your your tether that is your connection
to it it's your willingly
at every individual instance refusing to
give up
because you're not diligent enough
simple as that so the diligence is
measured and on that level not on how
many hours per day you stay awake and
sleep and how many how many how many
meditation sessions you have and how how
silent you are and how slow you walk and
it's how diligent you are in regard to
dispelling the unwholesome states and
purifying thoughts is their eyes
enduring them on the right level and not
taking out of it
so she given them up
fully she can't see anything that she
hasn't given up in terms of the five
lower Fetters
so how do you abandon the five lower
feathers by giving them up everything
that partakes in them choice
and you once you you're basically
restrained enough having kept the
precepts enough so you stop ignoring
your choice because automatically you
ignore the choice the choice is always
there you'd see that the take to touch
the loop to here you just ignore it
because it's just too quick too small
too little too insignificant seemingly
so
well if you are basically not ignoring
that choice the choice becomes apparent
and that's how you purify it and it's
Horizon
which is an amazing quality